### **IRENE PAREDES LOSADA**

#### **Environmental Scientist**

PhD in Environmental Sciences

#### BIO

I am a PhD in Environmental Sciences with background on aquatic ecology, management and conservation with special emphasis on water quality issues, eutrophication processes and human perturbations. Since 2009 I have worked in different research and interdisciplinary teams of recognized experience and prestige in Spain, the Netherlands, Brazil and the United Kingdom doing research on a broad variety of aquatic systems from urban ponds and intermittent streams to coastal lagoons and marshes of cold, tropical and Mediterranean environments.

#### **PERSONAL INFO**

Date of birth: 17 October 1986

Citizen: Spain

**Driving licence:** Yes

#### CONTACT

irene.paredeslosada@gmail.com +34 637195360

#### Research Gate:

https://www.researchgate.net/prof

ile/Irene Paredes Losada

#### LANGUAGE SKILLS

Spanish: Native speaker

**English:** Advanced level. TOEFL iBT certificate. Score 91. April 2013 **Portuguese:** Intermediate level

French: Elementary level INFORMATIC SKILLS

- ArcGIS/QGIS
- R
- Excel
- Microsoft Office
- Photoshop
- Adobe Indesign

#### **ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS**

#### **PhD in Environmental Sciences**

Doñana Biological Station (EBD-CSIC) Oct 2014 - Apr 2020

- *PhD thesis title:* "Anthropogenic pressures and eutrophication in the Doñana marsh and its watershed"
- PhD objective: to investigate the eutrophication issue in the Doñana wetland, a World Heritage Site in southwestern Europe by analyzing the spatio-temporal variation of nutrient pollution in surface waters and characterizing the sources of nitrogen by using stable nitrogen isotopes.
- Advisors: Andy J. Green, Francisco Ramírez and Manuela G. Forero
- Date of defense: 22nd April 2020

#### **MSc Environmental Sciences**

Wageningen University (WUR) Sept 2008 - Aug 2010

- Master thesis title: "Potential accumulation of the cyanotoxin cylindrospermopsin in non-producing phytoplanktonic species".
- Advisors: Miquel Lürling and Antonio Quesada
- Internship (4 months): Laboratory of Ecophysiology and Toxicology of Cyanobacteria. Institute of Biophysics Carlos Chagas Filho. Federal University of Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ). Brasil.

## 4-Year Bachelor in Environmental Sciences

Autónoma University of Madrid (UAM) Oct 2004 - Feb 2010

• Erasmus grant for one academic year at Wageningen University (WUR) from Sept. 2007 to June 2008.

## GRANTS AND FELLOWSHIPS

**Conference grant** to attend and present an oral communication at the AIL meeting in Murcia, 22 - 26 June 2020. Iberian Limnological Association (AIL).

Workshop grant to attend and present a poster communication at the "Temporary wetlands future in drylands under the projected global change scenario" workshop in Baeza, Spain, 9-11 March 2020. International University of Andalusia (UNIA) and Jaén University (UJA).

**Conference grant** to attend the First Meeting of the Iberian Ecological Society in Barcelona, 04 - 07 Feb 2019. Iberian Ecological Society (SIBECOL).

**PhD Fellowship.** "La Caixa" Foundation under the Severo Ochoa Program for Centers of Excellence, Spain. Oct 2014 - Oct 2018.

**Fellowship for short research stay in The Netherlands.** Wageningen Institute for
Environment and Climate Research (WIMEK), The
Netherlands. Oct - Dec 2015.

Fellowship for short research stay in The Netherlands. Wageningen Institute for Environment and Climate Research (WIMEK), The Netherlands. Apr - Jul 2011 and Nov - Dec 2011.

## STUDY AND RESEARCH ABROAD

Aquatic Ecology and Water Quality
Management Department (AEW), Wageningen
University (WUR), Wageningen, The Netherlands.
Jul 2009 - Dec 2009; Aug - Oct 2011; Oct - Dec 2015

Freshwater Biological Association (FBA), Windermere, Cumbria UK. Jun 2013 - Aug 2014

**Laboratory of Ecophysiology and Toxicology of Cyanobacteria.** Institute of Biophysics Carlos
Chagas Filho, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro
(UFRJ), Brasil. *Apr 2010 - Aug 2010* 

**Wageningen University (WUR)**, Wageningen, The Netherlands. *Sept 2007 - Jun 2008* 

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

**Environmental technician. The Freshwater Biological Association (FBA).** Lake District,

Cumbria. UK. Jul - Aug 2014

Literature search on historical information to understand the present status of river basins and improve the water quality management in different UK catchments.

**Freshwater bioremediation researcher (KTP Associate).** The Freshwater Biological Association (FBA) and the University of Cumbria (UoC). Lake District, Cumbria. UK. *Jun 2013 - Apr 2014* 

I studied the potential use of freshwater mussels as a bioremediation tool to mitigate algal blooms and reduce turbidity in nuclear ponds.

**Research Assistant.** Laboratory of Aquatic Ecology and Water Quality Management Group.

Wageningen University, The Netherlands. *Aug - Oct* 2011

Project "Mitigating Cyanobacteria Nuisance" to get more insight in costs and effectiveness of measures to control eutrophication.

**Research collaborator.** Department of Wetland Ecology, Doñana Biological Station. Seville, Spain. *Jul 2012 - Apr 2013* 

Laboratory experiments to determine how salinity, temperature and presence of parasites may affect the feeding rates of the invasive brine shrimp *Artemia franciscana* compared to its European congener *Artemia parthenogenetica* in hypersaline ecosystems in the South of Spain.

**Student assistant.** Laboratory of Aquatic Ecology and Water Quality Management Group. Wageningen University, The Netherlands. *Jul - Dec* 2009

Project focused on the article 8 of the 2006/7/CE Bathing Water Directive to determine the potential health risks due to harmful cyanobacteria. I participated on the processing and chemical analysis of freshwater samples.

## CONTRIBUTIONS TO CONFERENCES

#### First Meeting of the Iberian Ecological Society

Barcelona University (UB), 4-7 Feb 2019 Collaboration with the organization committee and attendance

### XIX Conference of the Iberian Limnological Association (AIL)

Coimbra University (Portugal), 24-29 Jun 2018 Oral presentation

**Paredes, I.,** Ramírez, F., G. Forero, M., Green, A.J. Nitrogen stable isotopes ( $\delta$ 15N) in halophytes as a proxy for anthropogenic nitrogen pollution in intermittent Mediterranean wetlands.

### SEFS10 Symposium of European Freshwater Sciences

Olomouc (Czech Republic), 2 - 7 Jul 2017 Oral presentation

**Paredes, I.,** Ramírez, F., G. Forero, M., Bravo, M.A., López, S., Green, A.J. Identification of nitrogen pollution sources in the Donana wetlands (southwestern spain) using stable Isotopes

### ABE Aquatic Biodiversity and Ecosystems Conference

Liverpool (UK) 30 Aug - 4 Sept 2015 Oral presentation

**Paredes, I.,** Ramírez, F., G. Forero, M., Espinar, J.L., Green, A.J. Piecing together the water quality deterioration in the Doñana Marsh (southwestern Spain) over the past 20 years

#### **SETAC Europe 25th Annual Meeting**

Barcelona (Spain) 3 -7 May 2015

Poster (presented at conferenced by A. Koelmans)

**Paredes, I.**, Koelmans, A.A., , Besseling, E.. Interactions of microplastics with freshwater mussels (*Anodonta anatina*).

#### **ASLO Aquatic Sciences Meeting**

Granada, 22-27 Feb 2015 Poster

**Paredes I.**, Báñez C., López R., Ramírez F., Bravo M.A., G. Forero M., Green A. Stable isotopes as tracers of anthropogenic nutrient inputs in two different aquatic systems in southern Spain

#### Global Change in the Mediterranean Symposium

Seville (Spain), 15-16 Nov 2012

Poster

PM.I. Sánchez, B.B Georgiev, P. Nikolov, G. Vasileva, N. Varo, J. A. Amat, C. Matesanz, C. Ramo, **I. Paredes** & A.J. Green. The invasion of *Artemia franciscana* in the Mediterranean Region: a matter of parasites?

#### XIII Brazilian Limnology Conference

Natal, Brasil, 4-8 Sept 2011 Attendance

### Second Iberian Meeting of Cyanobacteria (CIC2011)

Seville, 7-8 Jul 2011 Attendance

#### **Environmental National Conference CONAMA10**

Madrid, 22-26 Nov 2010

Attendance

### VIII International Conference about Toxic Cyanobacteria (ICTC8)

Istambul (Turkey), 29 Aug - 4 Sept 2010

Paredes I., Wormer, L., Cirés, S., Lürling, M., Quesada, A.

Potential accumulation of cylindrospermopsin in phytoplanktonic species.

#### first Iberian Meeting of Cyanobacteria (CIC2009)

Porto (Portugal), 6-7 Jul 2009 Attendance

#### LIST OF PUBLICATIONS

**Paredes, I.**, Ramírez, F., Aragonés, D., Bravo, M.A., Forero, M.G., Green, A.J.. Ongoing anthropogenic eutrophication of the catchment area threatens the Doñana World Heritage Site (South-west Spain). *Submitted* 

**Paredes, I.**, Otero, N., Soler, A., Green, A.J., Soto, D.X. 2020. Agricultural and urban delivered nitrate pollution input to Mediterranean temporary freshwaters. Agric. Ecosyst. Environ. 294, 106859.

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agee.2020.106859

**Paredes, I.**, Ramírez, F., Forero, M.G., Green, A.J., 2019. Stable isotopes in helophytes reflect anthropogenic nitrogen pollution in entry streams at the Doñana World Heritage Site. Ecol. Indic. 97, 130–140.

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolind.2018.10.009

Sánchez, M. I., **I. Paredes**, M. Lebouvier, and A. J. Green. 2016. Functional role of native and invasive filter-feeders, and the effect of parasites: Learning from hypersaline ecosystems. PLoS One. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0161478

## WORKSHOPS AND MEETINGS

### Workshop "Temporary wetlands future in drylands under the projected global change

**scenario"** organized by the International University of Andalusia (UNIA) and Jaén University (UJA). Baeza (Spain) 9-11 March 2020 *Poster presentation* 

### Workshop for experts: "Strategic Plan for the Restoration of the Guadalquivir

**Estuary"** organized by WWF-Spain Sanlúcar de Barrameda (Spain) 3-4 Oct. 2019 *Participation* 

### International Workshop EBD-MABH organized by

Dr. Andy Green at Doñana Biological Station (EBD-CSIC)

Seville (Spain), 2-4 May 2018

Oral presentation

### Meeting CTM2007-30981-E: Expanding cyanobacteria studies and its impact in Spain

Faculty of Biology. Autónoma University of Madrid Madrid (Spain) 23 Jan 2009

Attendance

#### **PUBLIC OUTREACH**

### Interview for the National Spanish Council (CSIC) (February 2020)

http://www.d-andalucia.csic.es/es/noticia/un-estudio-liderado-por-csic-determina-principales-fuentes-contaminacion-por-nitratos-en

### Interview on the Spanish National Journal 'La Vanguardia' (Oct 2018)

https://www.lavanguardia.com/vida/20181011/4522 99398594/estudio-del-csic-alerta-de-lacontaminacion-por-actividad-humana-endonana.html

#### Participation on the 14th, 16th and 17th Sciences

Fair of Seville to teach about aquatic ecology to primary and secondary school students through interactive activities. Seville (Spain) 2016, 2018, 2019.

#### Participation on the European Researchers'

**Night** with a workshop for children about the importance of water for nature and society. Seville (Spain) Sept 2018.

#### COURSES

### Statistics with R software: linear models and extensions (25 hrs)

Doñana Biological Station (EBD-CSIC) 24-28 Sept 2018. Seville (Spain)

#### Advanced course on QGIS (30 hrs)

Doñana Biological Station (EBD-CSIC) 10-14 Sept 2018. Seville (Spain)

# Training school COST-SMIRES on biogeochemistry of intermittent streams: techniques and concepts (40 hrs)

Girona University (UdG) 25-29 Sept 2017. Caldes de Malavella (Spain)

#### Introduction to QGIS (30 hrs)

Doñana Biological Station (EBD-CSIC) 27-31 Mar 2017. Seville (Spain)

### Scientific writing and oral presentation for conferences (20 hrs)

Doñana Biological Station (EBD-CSIC) 18-21 Oct 2016. Seville (Spain)

### Temporal series applied to environmental data (33 hrs)

Doñana Biological Station (EBD-CSIC) 11-15 May 2015. Seville (Spain)

### Stable isotopes in ecology and environmental studies (30 hrs)

Doñana Biological Station (EBD-CSIC) 6-8- Oct 2014. Seville (Spain)

### Data analysis for aquatic ecologists using R (24 hrs)

Bournemouth University 24-27 Feb 2014. Bournemouth (UK)

## COLLABORATIVE SCIENCES PROJECTS

#### **Currently participating in the URBIFUN project:**

Urbanization effects on the relationship between microbial biodiversity and ecosystem functioning

The Project is meant to promote scientific networking among young researchers of the AIL (Young-AIL) and to create synergistic interactions that lead to new knowledge on limnology. https://urbifunjail.wixsite.com/urbifun